Guide to the Henry Joseph Browne Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Henry Joseph Browne Papers
1797-1980
(bulk 1944-1980).
Browne, Henry Joseph, 1919-1980.
18.9 linear ft 41 document boxes and 1 flat box.
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY l0027
MS# 0158
4078408
Historian, archivist, social activist, and onetime Roman Catholic priest, Browne taught at Catholic University of America (where he also served as University Archivist); St. Joseph's Seminary, Yonkers, N.Y.; Cathedral College; and Rutgers University. He was active in community affairs in New York and Paterson, N.J. His primary research interests were John Hughes, first archbishop of New York, and labor and church history.
Biographical Note
Father Henry Joseph Browne, born in the Hell's Kitchen neighborhood of Manhattan in 1919, was an historian, archivist, and community activist. He entered the Catholic priesthood as a young man and devoted himself, for a while, to a scholarly and ecclesiastical life. He received his Ph.D. in history from the Catholic University of America where he went on to serve as a faculty member in church history and the University Archivist. Upon leaving that position he returned to New York to teach first at St. Joseph's Seminary in Yonkers, then Cathedral College, and finally Rutgers University in New Jersey.
His primary research interests were in social and labor history as well as church history, particularly in New York City. He published a number of pamphlets and articles on these issues, and a book on the history of the Catholic Knights of Labor. Additionally, he did extensive research on and drafted a biography of John Hughes, the first archbishop of New York.
Upon Browne's return to New York after his tenure at the Catholic University of America, he became deeply involved in left-wing political activities and made a name for himself as a committed community and anti-war activist in the 1960s. He was active in both religious and secular social justice organizations such as the New York City Council against Poverty, the Catholic Committee on Urban Ministry, and the Priests' Senate. He strongly opposed the urban renewal activities displacing lower income tenants on New York's Upper West side and worked actively with community housing organizations such as the Strycker's Bay Housing Development to retain low-income housing options in New York City.
In the last decade of his life Browne left the priesthood, though he was never officially defrocked, and settled in Paterson, NJ with his long-time partner, Flavia Alaya, and their three children. He took a job with Rutgers University and continued teaching almost until his death in 1980.
Scope and Content
The collection contains material related both to Browne's work as an activist and an academic. A significant portion of the collection consists of Browne's research material on John Hughes, including Hughes's correspondence, letter books, and scrapbooks.
Arrangement
Items arranged in two series:
Series I: Research and Scholarship, 1792-1980
Subseries I.1: John Hughes Biographical Materials, 1792-1956
Subseries II.2: Scholarly Research-- Church and Social History, 1947-1980
Series II: Personal and Professional, 1944-1980
Subseries II.1: Correspondence, 194-1980 Subseries
II.2: Topical Files, 1957-1980
Subjects
Rutgers University.--Dept. of History.; Catholic Church.--Archdiocese of New York (N.Y.); Catholic Church--United States.; Fordham University.; Hughes, John, 1797-1864.; Guilday, Peter, 1884-1947.; Spellman, Francis, 1889-1967.; McCloskey, John, Cardinal, 1810-1885.; Cooke, Terence, 1921-1983.; Ryan, William Frederick, 1926-; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872.; Weed, Thurlow, 1797-1882.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; City planning--New York (State)--New York.; City planning--New Jersey--Paterson.; Biographies.; Photoprints; Clergy; Historians
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
07/11/86 M-86-07-11 Papers Alaya, Flavia Gift
Gift of Flavia Alaya, 1986.
- Series I: Research and Scholarship,1792-1980
  The Research and Scholarship Series contains Browne’s research material, published articles and drafts, and lecture and reading notes
  - Subseries 1: John Hughes Biographical Materials, 1792-1956
    This Subseries, which forms the bulk of the Research and Scholarship series, contains primary materials relating to Archbishop John Hughes, such as Hughes’s original correspondence and topical files, both arranged alphabetically. Hughes’s correspondence files include letters from such notable figures as Abraham Lincoln, Popes Leo XII, Gregory XVI, and Pius IX. William Henry Seward was also a regular correspondent. This subseries also contains typescripts and microfilmed copies of Hughes’s correspondence, as well as his letterbooks and scrapbooks. Additionally, the subseries contains material collected by other would-be biographers of Hughes, including an unpublished manuscript of a Hughes biography by Peter Guilday.
    - Correspondence-- A-Z, 1860-1895, (17 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 17)
    - Correspondence
      - A-R, 1826-1920, (18 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 18)
      - S-Y and Unknown, 1840-1880, (7 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 7)
      - Typescripts and Photocopies, 1827-1863, (6 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 8 to 13)
    - Correspondence-- McCloskey-- Typescript, 1835-1836 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence
      - Photostats (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Letterbooks, 1841-1854, (2 volumes) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Typescript of Letterbooks (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Photocopies, 1794 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Microfilm, 1986-1910 (5 rolls) (Box 6, Folder 2 to 7)
    - The Complete Works of John Hughes, vol. 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence--Father Smith (Box 7)
      - Letterbook, 1857-1859 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbooks, 1844-1861, (3 volumes) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Topical Files
      - St. John’s College-- Fordham, 1841-1846, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 4 to 5)
      - St. Joseph’s Seminary, 1845-1855 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - St. Patrick’s Cathedral, 1839 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Statistics on Catholic Population, 1848-1855 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Varela, Felix (Obituary by Hughes), circa 1855 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Thomas Cassidy’s Materials on Hughes
      - General (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - General-- Transferred to Guilday (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Clippings, 1933-1934 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1933-1934, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 4 to 5)
      - List of Clergy in New York, 1847-1895 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - McCloskey, Cardinal, 1879-1888 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - McGlynn Case Materials (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Murray, Nicholas-- Memoirs, 1862 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Notes on Hughes’s Meeting with Pope Leo XIII (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Peter Guilday’s Material on Hughes
      - Correspondence
        - Guilday, 1927-1937, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 2)
        - New York Negotiation, 1928-1946 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Sisters of Charity, 1827-1846 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - M.H. Ward, 1890-1909 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Research Notes, 1928-1930s
        - General, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 6 to 7)
        - Church History (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - Clippings (originals and photocopies), 1827-1861 (Box 11, Folder 2)
        - DuBois Material (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Hughes Genealogical Material (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Letters Referenced in Hassard’s John Hughes (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - McKenna Clan History (Box 11, Folder 6)
        - Notre Dame and Baltimore Archives Research (Box 11, Folder 7)
        - Research in Europe, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 8)
        - St. Patrick’s Cathedral Archives (Box 11, Folder 9)
        - San Francisco (Box 11, Folder 10)
        - Outline of Hughes Biography (Box 11, Folder 11)
        - Register of Documents in Jesuit Archives, Rome Relating to Hughes (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Manuscript of Hughes Biography, (4 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 13 to 16)
      - Manuscript of Hughes Biography, (3 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Henry Joseph Browne’s Hughes Biography, circa 1956
      - Research Notes, (4 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 4 to 8)
      - Research Notes, (6 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Drafts and Notes, (5 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Manuscript, (5 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1 to 5)
  - Subseries 2: Scholarly Research-- Church and Social History, 1947-1980
    This subseries is comprised of Browne’s research materials and published articles, including his master’s thesis, and extensive notes he used to prepare and present his classroom lectures. These files indicate Browne’s interest in church and social history.
    - Church History Research and Resources, (2 volumes) (Box 15, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Browne’s Publication List (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Publications-- General, 1956-1958 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Publications-- In Typescript (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Publications and Clippings, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Articles, 1952-1957 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Browne on Jack Egan, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - The Catholic Church in American Life, (2 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Catholic University of America-- Research Notes (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - “Catholics Face a New Frontier,” 1960 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Church History Articles, 1951-1956 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Church and Labor Research (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - “Diocesan Clergy of New York: An Historical Sketch,” 1950-1951 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - “The Faculty and the Archivist,” circa 1960s (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - “Groping for Relevance in an Urban Parish,” 1971 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - “Housing the Poor: The Confused Catholic Social Apostolate,” 1968 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - “Majority Interests,” 1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - “Maxima Vigilantia” (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Molly Maguires, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - “One Stop Above Hell’s Kitchen: Sacred Heart Parish in Clinton,” 1976, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Parochial Archives-- Notes, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - “Power and the Institutional Church,” 1967 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - “A Preliminary Survey of the Historical Bibliography of the Archdiocese of New York,” 1946 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - “St. Ann’s on East Twelfth Street New York City, 1852-1952,” 1952 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - “Terence Powderley: His Relationship with the Catholic Church,” 1945 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      (Browne’s Master’s Thesis)
    - “Toward Symbolic, Theopolitical Ministry” (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Urban Renewal-- Various. 1966 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Teaching Materials
      - American Community, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Church History-- Catholic University of America, (2 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Church History-- St. Joseph’s (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Civil War and the Church (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Comparative Social Movements, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Medieval History, 1967 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Notes, 1952-1970s, (3 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 8 to 10)
- Series II: Personal and Professional, 1944-1980
  This series relates to Browne’s professional duties as a priest, academic, and an archivist, as well as his involvement in community and social justice organizations.
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence, 1944-1980
    The correspondence subseries includes one run of correspondence that is arranged chronologically, and one run of Browne’s correspondence that is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. There is no significant difference in the content or research value of these runs.
    - 1944-1953, (7 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 7)
    - 1954-1956, (6 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 1 to 6)
    - 1957-1960, (7 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 1 to 7)
    - 1961-1968, (7 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 1 to 7)
    - 1968-1969, (6 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 1 to 6)
    - 1970 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 1979 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - 1980 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - 1980-- Condolence Letters (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Regarding John Carroll, 1958-1959 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Regarding John Hughes Biography, 1949-1956, (2 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Regarding Knights of Labor, 1949-1950 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - A-Z, 1944-1969, (10 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 1 to 10)
    - Society of American Archivists, 1944-1957, (4 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 11 to 14)
  - Subseries 2: Topical Files, 1949-1980
    This subseries contains files relating to Browne’s political and professional life, including his work with the New York City Council Against Poverty, and his work with faith-based social justice organizations including the Catholic Committee Urban Ministry. These files are arranged alphabetically.
    - Book Reviews, 1950-1977 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Cathedral College, 1961 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Catholic Archives, 1950 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Catholic Charities, 1959-1960 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Catholic Committee on Urban Ministry (CCUM)
      - General, 1973-1980, (3 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 5 to 7)
      - General, 1973-1980, (4 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Board of Directors’ Correspondence, 1976-1980 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Bulletins, Newsletters, and Printed Material, 1974-1979 (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1977 (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - Liberty and Justice for All Conference, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 8)
      - Memoranda, 1972-1975, (2 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Clippings, 1949-1980, (3 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 3 to 5)
    - Dictionary of American Biograph y Entries, 1956 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Ethnic Parishes, 1974-1979 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Fulbright Award, 1957 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Internal Life of the Church, 1959-1960 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Italian-Americans (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Kelleher, Stephen, 1977 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Life Magazine, 1960 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Mediating Structures Project, 1977 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Modernism in Religion, 1963 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - New York City Council Against Poverty
      - General, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - Agendas, 1967-1968, (3 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 6 to 8)
      - Agendas, 1968, (4 Folders) (Box 30, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Bulletins, 1967-1968 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - Memoranda, 1967-1968 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      - Memoranda, 1968, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Minutes, 1967-1968, (3 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 3 to 5)
    - New York Times Letters, 1965 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Parish Schools, Undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, Undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Priests’ Senate
      - General, 1966-1969, (6 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Protestant Social Reform, Undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Puck Cartoons-- Church and Labor (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Religions and the Labor Movement, Undated (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Rutgers University
      - Administrative, 1969-1979, (4 Folders) (Box 33, Folder 2 to 5)
      - Sociology Department, 1976-1978 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - St. Gregory’s Parish-- Staff Meetings and Notes, 1968 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Shaw, Richard, 1977 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Task Force on Social Ministries, 1980 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Vatican Council (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - West Park Religious Council, 1959 (Box 34, Folder 5)
- Series III. Urban Planning and Community Organizing, 1959-1979
  This series chronicles Browne's involvement in urban planning and urban renewal initiatives in New York City and Paterson, New Jersey.
  - Subseries 1: Paterson, New Jersey, 1972-1979
    This subseries contains Browne's files relating to his work with organizations such as the Paterson Coalition, a coalition of local community organizations working together for the general betterment of their community, and local groups committed to historic preservation.
    - Correspondence, 1972-1979, (2 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Great Falls Development Corporation, 1973-1979 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - History, 1977-1979 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - INCCA Carroll Street Housing, 1977-1979 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Minutes and Agendas (Various Groups), 1973-1978 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Paterson Coalition, 1973-1976, (2 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Save Paterson’s Living American Social Heritage (SPLASH), 1975 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: West Side Urban Renewal, 1959-1979
    This subseries documents Browne's involvement in issues of urban renewal on New York's Upper West Side. Notably, it documents the development and early activities of the Strycker’s Bay Neighborhood Council and Strycker's Bay Housing Development, including correspondence, meeting minutes and agendas, and manuscript and printed material dealing with the development of the Upper West Side of Manhattan.
    - General, 1964-1979, (3 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 1 to 3)
    - City-Wide Squatter’s Movement, 1971 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Clippings, 1973-1974 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Clippings-- Broadway Local, Undated (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Joint Parish Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - New York City Housing Authority, 1974-1976 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Publications and Manuscripts, 1960s (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Ratensky, Samuel, 1959 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Redevelopment Sites, 1971-1974 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Religious Organizations, 1961-1963 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Reports and Plans, 1960 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Sacred Heart Parish Centennial, 1977 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Statements and Press Releases, 1961-1962 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Strycker’s Bay Cooperative, 1960-1969, (2 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Strycker’s Bay Neighborhood Council
      - General, 1960-1979, (4 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 3 to 6)
      - General, 1967-1979, (6 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 1 to 6)
      - General, 1980 and Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 1 to 2)
      - General, Microfilm (Box 40, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1971, (5 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 4 to 8)
      - Correspondence-- Schafer, Roger, 1960-1961 (Box 41, Folder 1)
      - Community Action Projects, 1966-1967, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Housing Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 41, Folder 4)
      - Legal Documents, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 5)
      - New York City Board of Estimate, 1970-1971 (Box 41, Folder 6)
      - New York City Housing Authority, 1968-1973 (Box 41, Folder 7)
      - Newsletters and Announcement, 1970-1971 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - Project Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      - Relocation Committee, 1960 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      - Reports, 1967-1970 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      - Statement of the Role of Federal Government in Urban Affairs, 1966 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - West Side Neighborhood Organizations, 1959-1960 (Box 42, Folder 6)